Northern Pacific Railroad, Minnesota Division, Labor Records 5600
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Northern Pacific Railroad Minnesota Division, Labor Records
1903-1945
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Northern Pacific Railroad (NP)
McClelland, A. W. (Trainamster)
Gregory, T. A. (Trainmaster)
Hackenberg, E. J. (Superintendent)
Flynn, T. M. (Superintendent)
5600
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Claims, records.
This collection consists chiefly of claims cases brought before the Train Service Board of Adjustment for the Western Region; also present are letter press books containing certificates of examination and documentation of employee termination from the Northern Pacific facility in Staples, Minnesota, correspondence from the superintendent, and reports on cabooses.
2295994
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, April 06, 2017
EAD encoding:
E. Parker, April 06, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Northern Pacific Railroad Company [NP] was a transcontinental railroad that operated across the northern part of the continental United States from Minnesota to the Puget Sound. It was organized in 1864 with a charter by the United States Congress signed by President Abraham Lincoln. Construction in both Minnesota and Washington Territory (now Washington State) began in 1870. The lines were joined in western Montana in 1883, where former president Ulysses S. Grant drove in the golden spike. The railroad was fully completed in 1888 when a tunnel under the Cascade Mountains was completed, replacing a series of switchbacks over Stampede Pass that had been used as a temporary measure to transverse the natural barrier.
The NP was headquartered in St. Paul Minnesota, and its trackage and operations were organized into regional divisions. These regions changed over time (see Northern Pacific Railway Historical Association's "NP Division Evolution") as the railroad expanded its operations. The Minnesota Division, later called the St. Paul Division, was predominantly the area stretching from the Great Lakes to the Minnesota - North Dakota border. The main routes were St. Paul to Staples, Minnesota; St. Paul to White Bear Lake; and Staples to Dilworth, Minnesota.
Although this collection is from the Minnesota Division, there are reports from other divisions, such as Fargo, Dakota and Yellowstone, in the correspondence and claims files.
The NP was famous for its passenger service from Chicago to Seattle on the North Coast Limited train. It was also a major transporter of freight across the northern United States. In addition to providing access to newly opened lands, the NP also aided in their settlement by white Europeans, opening colonization offices in Germany and the Scandinavian countries, where they attracted immigrants with cheap but productive farmland, whose goods were then transported on NP trains. These populations settled primarily in Minnesota and the Dakota territories.
The NP also hired large numbers of Chinese laborers, mostly from the southern provinces around Hong Kong, though some may have been previously employed in the building of the Central Pacific Railroad. It is estimated by BNSF, the NP's successor railroad, that 15,000 of the 25,000 required laborers needed in 1882 ( source)were Chinese immigrants. However unlike their German and Scandinavian counterparts, there are minimal records about these employees.
In addition to its key role in the westward expansion of the United States, the NP was also an innovator in technology, pioneering locomotive designs such as the 4-8-4, called the Northern, and the 2-8-8-4, called the Yellowstone.
In 1970, NP merged with the Chicago, Burlington and Quincy Railroad and the Great Northern Railway to form the Burlington Northern Railroad Company. In 1996, the Burlinton Norther merged with the Santa Fe Railway to form the Burlington Northern and Santa Fe Railway [BNSF], one of the largest freight railroads in the United States, and as of 2007 one of seven remaining North American Class I railroads.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1903 - 1945
Bulk dates: 1903 - 1945
This collection consists of records from the Northern Pacific Railroad Company, Minnesota division. The majority of records present in the collection are concerned with employees and labor relations, although there are also records documenting the daily operations of the train yards. Of note in this regard are the Caboose Reports (1941-1945) written by superintendent T. M. Flynn, which document the assignment of cabooses, i.e. if they were in service, out of service, serviceable, or unserviceable. Also of note is the correspondence regarding efficiency tests and operating risks and rules by trainmasters and superintendents.
The labor records include a letter press book (1904-1909) of certificates of examination for positions of conductor and locomotive engineer on the Minnesota Division of the Northern Pacific Railway; a letter press book (1903-1907) documenting and recording dismissals and resignations of Northern Pacific Railway employees at Minneapolis, as well as the reason why employment has been terminated; and a series of monthly reports from 1945 that document employees leaving the company. Also of note is a ruling from the United States Railroad Administration, Railway Board of Adjustment No. 1, regarding yard work on Sundays.
The majority of the labor records consist of claims cases brought before the Train Service Board of Adjustment for the Western Region involving the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers [BLE] and the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen [BLF&E] vs. the Northern Pacific Railway (1929-1934) regarding seniority, runaround, wages, additional mileage, overtime, work schedule, reporting pay, deadhead payment, deadhead mileage, pay rates (local and freight), work assignments, pay for time lost, and pay for work performed outside of position description. Other claims cases heard by the Train Service Board of Adjustment for the Western Region involve the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen [BRT] and the Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen [ORC] vs. the Northern Pacific Railroad Company (1925-1933) regarding wage rates, mileage, overtime, deadheading, pay for work performed outside of position description; and time claims, with attached letters from E.J. Hackenberg (superintendent) regarding the dispute resolutions, decisions, claims, and contract rules. There is a general synopsis of many of these cases, summarizing decision nos. 2601-4200.
The correspondence folders are arranged chronologically. The case decision folders are organized by decision number.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5553: Northern Pacific Railway Co. Reports and Correspondence of Trainmaster
Cabooses (Railroads); Trainmaster (locomotive); Arbitration, Industrial -- Railroads -- United States; Railroads -- Employees -- Dismissal of -- Minnesota -- Minneapolis; Hours of labor -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Job descriptions -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Labor disputes -- Railroads -- Minnesota; Labor productivity -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Locomotive engineers -- Minnesota -- Examinations; Railroad conductors -- Minnesota -- Examinations; Railroads -- Personnel management -- United States; Seniority, Employee -- Law and legislation -- United States; Wages -- Railroads -- United States; Work assignments -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Employee rules -- United States; Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (U.S.); Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen; Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen; Northern Pacific Railway Company. Minnesota Division; Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen; Northern Pacific Railway Company.
2295994
- Volume of Notices of Discharge or Resignation, Nos. 19 to 487, Inclusive., 1903-1907 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  November 28, 1903 - October 24, 1907. Staple, Minnesota. Partial index of names. Letter press book. (EXTREMELY FRAGILE).
- Volume of Certificates of Examination for the Position of Conductor or Engineer, 1904-1909 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Pages 9 - 354. Letter press book missing front cover and first few leaves. (EXTREMELY FRAGILE)
- Train Service Board of Adjustment for the Western Region, Decisions No. 3122-3141, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  BLE and BLF&E vs. NP Railway Company
- Train Service Board of Adjustment for the Western Region, Decisions No. 3378, 3399, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Train Service Board of Adjustment for the Western Region, Decisions No. 3400-3403, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 3a)
- Train Service Board of Adjustment for the Western Region, Decisions No. 3552-3554, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 3b)
- Train Service Board of Adjustment for the Western Region, Decisions No. 3837-3850, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 4a)
- Train Service Board of Adjustment for the Western Region, Decisions No. 3851-3892, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 4b)
- Train Service Board of Adjustment for the Western Region, Decisions No. 5780-5798, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Train Service Board of Adjustment for the Western Region, Decisions No. 5800-5868, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence re efficiency tests and operating risks, 1926-1945 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  From offices of trainmasters and superintendents
- U.S. Railroad Administration. Railway Board of Adjustment No. 1, Ruling, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  NP Railway Co. and Trainmen, Claim of Yardmen at Forsyth for time lost account road crews used to perform yard service on Sundays.
- Train Service Board of Adjustment for the Western Region, General Synopsis of Decision No.s 2601 - 4200, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Train Service Board of Adjustment for the Western Region, Decision No.s 1376, 1503, 1924, 1925-1933 (Box 3, Folder 3a)
  BRT vs. NP Railway Co.; ORC vs. NP Railway Co.
- Train Service Board of Adjustment for the Western Region, Decision No. 2228, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 3b)
- Train Service Board of Adjustment for the Western Region, Decision No.s 3864-3894, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 3c)
- Train Service Board of Adjustment for the Western Region, Decision No.s 4274-4391, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 3d)
- Train Service Board of Adjustment for the Western Region, Decision No.s 5246-5280, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 3e)
- Correspondence of Superintendent, E. J. Hackenberg, 1917-1934 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Employees Leaving Service, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Caboose Report, 1941-1945 (Box 3, Folder 6)